Tonight, I'm going to share with you my passion for science.
오늘밤 저는 과학에 대한 제 열정을 공유하고 싶습니다.
I'm not talking about science that takes baby steps.
걸음마를 하는 과학을 이야기하는게 아닙니다.
I'm talking about science that takes enormous leaps.
새로운 지평을 여는 과학을 이야기하겠습니다.
I'm talking Darwin, I'm talking Einstein,
다윈, 아인쉬타인을 얘기합니다.
I'm talking revolutionary science that turns the world on its head.
세상을 뒤엎는 혁신적인 과학을 얘기합니다.
In a moment, I'm going to talk about two ideas that might do this.
어쩌면 곧 이런 일을 할 두 가지 생각을 얘기하겠습니다.
I say "might"
"어쩌면"이라고 했는데
because, with revolutionary ideas, most are flat wrong,
혁신적인 아이디어는 대부분 아주 틀렸거나
and even those that are right seldom have the impact
옳다고 하더라고 우리가 원하는 식의 효과를
that we want them to have.
거의 끼치지 못하기 때문이죠.
To explain why I picked two ideas in particular,
왜 특별히 두 아이디어를 골랐는지 설명하기 위해
I'm going to start with a mystery.
수수께끼를 먼저 얘기할게요.
1847, Vienna, Austria.
1847년 오스트리아 비엔나.
Ignaz Semmelweis was a somber, compulsively thorough doctor
이그나즈 젬멜바이스는 엄격하고 철두철미한 의사로
who ran two maternity clinics.
두 산부인과를 운영했습니다.
They were identical except for one thing.
두 병원은 한 가지만 빼고 똑같았죠.
Women were dying of high fevers soon after giving birth
출산한 직후 고열로 죽는 여자들이
three times more often at one of the clinics than at the other.
한 병동이 다른 병동보다 3배 많았습니다.
Trying to figure out what the difference was that caused this,
이런 차이를 일으키는 원인을 알고자
Semmelweis looked at everything he could.
젬멜바이스는 모든 곳을 찾았습니다.
Sanitation? No.
위생? 아니.
Medical procedures? No.
치료 과정? 아니.
Air flow? No.
공기 흐름? 아니.
The puzzle went unsolved until he happened to autopsy a doctor
감염된 수술칼 상처로 죽은 의사를 부검할 때까지
who died of an infected scalpel cut.
그 문제를 해결하지 못했습니다.
The doctor's symptoms were identical to those of the mothers who were dying.
의사의 증상은 죽은 산모들과 같았습니다.
How was that possible?
어떻게 그럴 수 있을까요?
How could a male doctor get the same thing as new mothers?
남자 의사가 어떻게 산모와 같은 증상을 가질 수 있나요?
Semmelweis reconstructed everything the doctor had done
그 의사가 아프기 직전까지 했던 모든 일을 젬멜바이스가 재구성하여
and he discovered that he'd been autopsying a corpse.
의사가 시체를 부검하고 있었음을 밝혀냈습니다.
Had something gotten in his wound that killed him?
상처에 들어간 뭔가가 그를 죽였을까?
With growing excitement,
커져가는 흥분과 함께
Semmelweis looked for any connection he could
젬멜바이스는 영안실의 시체와
between dead bodies in the morgue and dead mothers in his delivery room,
분만실의 죽은 임산부 사이에 어떤 연관이 있는지 살폈고
and he found it.
그것을 찾아냈습니다.
It turned out that at the hospital with the high death rate,
다른 병동이 아닌
but not the others,
높은 사망율을 보인 병동에서는
doctors delivered babies immediately after autopsying corpses in the morgue.
의사들이 영안실의 시체를 부검한 직후 아기를 받았습니다.
Aha! Corpses were contaminating the doctors' hands
아! 시체가 의사의 손을 오염시켰고
and killing his mothers.
임산부를 죽였죠.
So he ordered the doctors to sterilize their hands,
그는 의사들에게 손을 소독하도록 명령했고
and the deaths stopped.
사망사건이 멈췄습니다.
Dr. Ignaz Semmelweis had discovered infectious disease.
이그나즈 젬멜바이스 의사가 전염병을 발견했죠.
But the doctors of the day thought he was crazy,
그러나 그 당시 의사들은 그가 미쳤다고 생각했습니다.
because they knew, and had for hundreds of years,
그들은 수백년 동안
that odorous vapors called miasmas caused disease,
지저분한 공기라고 하는 냄새나는 증기가 질병을 일으킨다고 생각했죠.
not these hypothetical particles that you couldn't see.
볼 수 없는 이러한 가설의 입자가 아니고요.
It took 20 years for Frenchman Louis Pasteur
프랑스인 루이스 파스퇴르가 젬멜바이스가 옳았음을 증명하는데
to prove that Semmelweis was right.
20년이 걸렸습니다.
Pasteur was an agricultural chemist
파스퇴르는 농업에 관한 화학자로
who tried to figure out why milk and beer spoiled so often.
왜 우유와 맥주가 그렇게 자주 상하는지 알아내려 했습니다.
He found that bacteria were the culprits.
그는 박테리아가 주범임을 알아냈죠.
He also found that bacteria could kill people in exactly the same way
박테리아가 사람을 죽일 수 있다는 것도 알아냈습니다.
that Semmelweis's patients were dying.
젬멜바이스의 환자가 죽은 것과 같은 방식이죠.
We now look at what I want to talk about tonight, in two ideas.
이제 제가 오늘밤 얘기하고 싶은 두 아이디어를 보시죠.
We saw it with Semmelweis, that he was a revolutionary.
젬멜바이스의 예에서 그는 혁신적이었습니다.
He did it for two reasons.
두 가지 이유에서 그렇습니다.
One, he opened our eyes to a completely new world.
하나, 그는 우리에게 완전히 새로운 세상을 보여줬습니다.
We'd known since the 1680s about bacteria.
우리는 1680년부터 박테리아에 대해 알았습니다.
We just didn't know that bacteria killed people.
박테리아가 사람을 죽인다는 것은 몰랐죠.
And he also demolished fond ideas that people kept close to their heart.
그는 또한 사람들이 가슴깊이 간직했던 아이디어도 뒤집었습니다.
Miasmas didn't kill people. Bacteria killed people.
지저분한 공기가 아니라 박테리아가 사람을 죽였습니다.
So this brings me to the two ideas I want to talk about tonight.
이것이 제가 오늘밤 얘기하려는 두 아이디어로 이끌게 하는군요.
One has opened our eyes to a completely new universe,
하나는 완전히 새로운 세상을 보여주고
and the other attacks long-held beliefs.
다른 하나는 오랜 믿음을 뒤집습니다.
Let's get started with Dr. Eric Betzig.
에릭 베치그 박사 얘기를 해보죠.
He's a physicist who has opened our eyes to an entirely new world
그는 물리 법칙을 뒤엎고 완전히 새로운 세상을
by violating the laws of physics.
보여준 물리학자입니다.
Betzig is a true rebel.
베치그는 진정한 반항아입니다.
He quit a job at prestigious Bell Laboratory
그는 생물학을 위한 새로운 현미경을 발명한
inventing new microscopes for biology
유명한 벨 실험실을 관뒀습니다.
because he thought scientists were taking his brilliant inventions
그가 만든 뛰어난 발명품으로 과학자들이 형편없는 연구를 한다고
and doing lousy work with them.
생각했기 때문입니다.
So he became a househusband,
그는 전업남편이 되었지만
but he never lost his passion for figuring out
탐구하려는 열정을 결코 놓치지 않았습니다.
how to get microscopes to see finer and finer details
전에 본 적이 없는, 볼 수 없었던 더욱 정교한 내용을
than had ever been seen before or ever could be seen.
볼 수 있는 현미경을 개발하는 열정이죠.
This is crucial if we're ever going to understand how cells work,
세포가 어떻게 일하고 암이 어떻게 퍼지는지 이해하려면
and how cancer works,
이것은 중요합니다.
and how something 150th the size of a head of a pin
핀 머리의 1/150 크기밖에 안 되는 것이 어떻게 해서
can do all these amazing things,
이런 놀라운 일을 할까요.
like make proteins
단백질을 만들거나
and move charges around
전하를 옮기거나
and all of those things.
다양한 일을 하는거죠.
There's just one problem.
한 가지 문제가 있습니다.
There's this thing called the law of physics,
물리법칙이란 것이 있는데
and part of the law of physics is the thing called the diffraction limit.
물리법칙의 일부에 회절 한계가 있습니다.
The diffraction limit is kind of like when you go to a doctor's office,
회절 한계는 여러분이 의사 진료실에 가서
you can only see so far down, no matter how good glasses you have.
아무리 좋은 안경을 끼고 있어도 아래쪽까지만 볼 수 있는 것과 같죠.
This was a so-called impossible problem.
이것은 불가능한 문제였습니다.
But one of Betzig's friends figured out how to take a tiny molecule
그러나 베치그의 친구 중 한 명이 최고의 현미경으로
that was smaller than the best microscope could see
볼 수 있는 것보다 더 작은 분자를
and get it to light up and fluoresce.
밝히고 형광을 발하는 법을 알아냈죠.
"Aha!" Betzig said.
"아" 베치그가 말했습니다.
"I think maybe the laws of physics are not so unbreakable after all."
"물리법칙은 깰 수 없는 것이 아닌지도 몰라"
So he lashed together a microscope in his friend's living room.
그는 친구의 거실에서 현미경을 조립했습니다.
He had no laboratory.
그는 실험실이 없었습니다.
This revolutionary instrument got different protein molecules
이 혁신적인 기구는 다른 단백질 분자를
to light up in different colors,
다른 색깔로 빛나게 해서
and with a computer, he was able to turn very, very fuzzy blurs
컴퓨터를 써서 아주 흐릿하고 희미한 것을
into very sharp dots and produce images of unprecedented and startling clarity.
아주 날카로운 점으로 변환시켜 전례없이 선명한 이미지를 만들었죠.
For this work, last year,
이 성과로 인해 작년
Eric Betzig won the Nobel Prize.
에릭 베치그는 노벨상을 탔습니다.
Why?
왜죠?
Because now we can see with unprecedented detail
이전에는 본 적이 없었던 전례없는 세부사항을
things that we never had seen before,
이제 볼 수 있기 때문이죠.
and now doctors can get a better handle on things like cancer.
이제 의사들은 암과 같은 것을 더 잘 다룰 수 있습니다.
But do you think Betzig was satisfied there?
베치그가 여기서 만족했을까요?
No.
아니오.
He wanted movies.
그는 영상을 원했습니다.
The problem was
문제는
that even the genius microscopes that he invented were just too slow.
그가 발명한 천재적인 현미경도 너무 느렸다는 거죠.
So what did he do?
그는 어떻게 했을까요?
He came up with a 200-year-old idea
그는 200년 된 아이디어를 떠올렸습니다.
called moiré patterns.
무아레 무늬라는 것입니다.
So the way that works is if you take two very, very fine patterns
설명을 드리자면 두 개의 아주 미세한 무늬를
and you move them across each other,
서로 교차시키면
you will see a gross pattern
현미경이 볼 수 있는 거친 무늬를 볼 수 있습니다.
that otherwise you would not be able to see.
그렇지 않으면 볼 수가 없죠.
So he applied this technique to taking a really blurry image of a cell
그는 이 기술을 아주 흐린 세포 이미지에 적용시켜
and moving lots of structured light patterns across it
구조화된 빛의 다양한 패턴을 교차시켜
until this cell became crystal clear.
이 세포가 아주 뚜렷해지도록 만들었습니다.
And here is the result:
그 결과입니다.
a mysterious new world,
신비로운 새 세상으로
full of strange things zipping around
이상한 것들이 가득 돌아다니며
doing things that we don't know what they're doing.
우리가 모르는 일을 합니다.
But when we figure it out, we'll have a better handle on life itself.
하지만 우리가 그것을 밝혀내면 생명 자체를 잘 다룰 수 있습니다.
For example, those green globs that you see?
예를 들어, 초록색 방울이 보입니까?
Those things are called clathrins.
클라트린이라는 건데요.
They're molecules that protect other molecules
세포 사이를 움직이며 다른 분자를
as they move through a cell.
보호하는 분자입니다.
Unfortunately, viruses sometimes hijack those to infect cells.
불행히도 바이러스가 세포를 감염시키려고 이것을 납치합니다.
Also, you see those little squiggly wormlike things moving around?
벌레처럼 꿈틀거리며 돌아다니는게 보입니까?
Those are actin molecules.
액틴 분자입니다.
Unfortunately, viruses also climb down those things
불행히도 바이러스는 이것들을 타고 내려가
to get into the cell nucleus
세포핵으로 들어가
to replicate themselves and make you sick.
자가복제하여 여러분을 아프게 만들죠.
Now that we can look at movies
이제 우리는 세포 속 깊은 곳에서
of what's actually going on deep inside a cell,
무슨 일이 벌어지는지 영화로 볼 수 있습니다.
we have a much better chance of curing viral diseases like AIDS.
에이즈 같은 바이러스 질환을 치료할 더 나은 기회가 왔습니다.
So when you look at a movie like this,
여러분이 이렇게 영화로 보면
it's very clear that Betzig has opened our eyes to a completely new world.
베치그가 아주 새로운 세상을 보여준 것이 분명합니다.
But he hasn't shattered any cherished beliefs.
하지만 그는 간직해온 믿음을 깨지 않았죠.
That leads us to Dr. Aubrey de Grey
캠브리지의 오브리 드 그레이 박사를 보시겠습니다.
De Grey definitely has scientists squirming with an interesting idea:
드 그레이는 흥미로운 아이디어로 활동하는 과학자입니다.
we can be immortal.
우리는 불멸할 수 있어요.
We can beat aging.
우리는 노화를 무찌를 수 있어요.
Now, most scientists think he's a crackpot.
대부분의 과학자들은 그가 괴짜라고 생각합니다.
Any Biology 101 student knows
생물학 개론을 들은 학생은 모두
that aging is an inevitable consequence of living.
노화는 삶의 불가피한 결과임을 압니다.
For example, when we eat,
예를 들어, 우리가 먹을 때
we take in food and we metabolize it,
음식을 먹고 대사 작용을 하면
and that throws off what we call free radicals.
유해 산소가 나옵니다.
You might have heard of those.
들어본 적이 있죠.
Also known as oxygen ions,
산소 이온으로도 알려졌는데
those bind to our DNA, cause it to mutate,
DNA와 결합하여 돌연변이를 일으키고
and cause us to get old and lose our hair.
우리를 늙게 하고 머리카락을 잃게 만듭니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
It's just like, no, it's exactly like
마치, 아니 정확히 이렇습니다.
oxygen binding to iron and making it rust.
산소가 철과 결합해서 녹슬게 만들죠.
So you age because you rust out.
여러분은 녹슬기 때문에 늙습니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
Oh, and scientists also know there is something called immortality:
과학자들도 불멸이 있음을 압니다.
in cancer cells.
암세포에 있죠.
So if you stop aging,
여러분이 늙지 않는다면
all of you are going to turn into giant walking malignant tumors.
여러분은 모두 걸어다니는 거대한 악성 종양이 될 것입니다.
These are cherished beliefs, but could de Grey be on to something?
이런 것을 믿었는데 드 그레이가 뭔가를 할 수 있을까요?
I think he deserves a closer look.
그를 잘 살펴볼 가치가 있어요.
First of all, I have a really hard time seeing him as a crackpot.
우선 저는 그를 괴짜로 보기 어렵습니다.
Yeah, he started off life as a computer scientist,
그는 생물학자가 아니라
not a biologist,
컴퓨터 과학자로 시작했지만
but he earned a PhD in biology from Cambridge,
캠프리지에서 생물학으로 박사학위를 받았어요.
and he has published some very significant work
그는 미토콘드리아 DNA와 여러 가지 다른 것에 관해
on mitochondrial DNA and a bunch of other stuff.
아주 중요한 연구를 발표했습니다.
Secondly, he started an antiaging foundation
둘째, 노화방지 재단을 설립해서
that has identified seven different causes of aging,
노화의 7가지 다른 원인을 밝혔습니다.
to me, that seem very plausible,
저한테는 그럴듯해 보입니다.
and he is hot in pursuit of fixes for every single one of them.
그는 각각의 원인을 고치려고 열심히 노력하고 있습니다.
For example, one of the reasons we age is that our mitochondrial DNA mutates,
예를 들어, 늙는 이유 중 하나는 미토콘드리아 DNA가 돌연변이가 되어
and we get kind of old and our cells lose energy.
우리가 늙고 세포는 에너지를 잃습니다.
He believes, and he's made a convincing case,
그는 설득력있는 예를 만들었고
that using viruses we can do gene therapy,
바이러스를 이용해 유전자 치료를 할 수 있다고 믿습니다.
fix that DNA
DNA를 고쳐서
and rejuvenate our cells.
세포에 활기를 넣는거죠.
One more thing.
한 가지 더.
We have an existent proof
엄청난 장수가 가능하다는 증거가 있습니다.
Bristlecone pine trees live 5,000 years,
브리슬콘 소나무는 5천년을 살고
and some lobsters don't age at all.
바다가재는 전혀 늙지 않습니다.
Now, this doesn't mean that de Grey is going to revolutionize our lifespans.
드 그레이가 우리의 수명에 혁명을 가져온다는 뜻은 아닙니다.
I mean, after all, we're not trees, and most of us are not lobsters.
어쨌든 우리는 나무도 아니고 바다가재도 아닙니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
But I've got to believe that there are Darwins and Einsteins out there,
하지만 다윈이나 아인쉬타인 같은 사람들이 있다고 믿습니다.
and I'll tell you why.
왜인지 말씀드리죠.
Consider this:
이것을 살펴보세요.
there are seven times more people alive today than during Darwin's time.
다윈의 시대보다 7배나 많은 사람이 오늘날 살고 있습니다.
There are four times as many people alive today as Einstein.
아인쉬타인 시대보다 4배나 많은 사람이 있고요.
When you consider
생각해보세요.
that the proportion of scientists in the population has skyrocketed,
인구 중에서 과학자의 비율이 급증했습니다.
there are now seven million scientists.
이제 7백만 명의 과학자가 있습니다.
I've got to believe, and I do believe, that there's one of them out there
저는 믿어야 하고 믿습니다. 밖에 있는 그들 중 한 명은
who is working right now in obscurity
지금 무명속에서 우리 삶을 흔들 연구를 하고 있습니다.
but I can't wait to be rocked.
저는 그 때를 기다릴 수 없군요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
(Applause)
(박수)